A Guide to the Wilbur G. Downs Papers FA055
Rockefeller Archive Center
Wilbur G. Downs papers
1928-1950, 1964-1976, 1981, undated
Rockefeller Archive Center
Downs, Wilbur G.
Rockefeller Foundation
FA055
1.4 Cubic Feet 5 document cases
Arrangement note
This collection is arranged in three series:
Series 1 - Correspondence
Series 2 - Diaries
Series 3 - Laboratory Studies
Conditions Governing Access
Open for scholarly research except where particular restrictions are noted.
RAC is unable to provide access to obsolete media and original digital media. In addition separated media may not yet have undergone stabilization procedures. When feasible, a digital surrogate may be created via special order. All applicable charges will apply. See RAC Head of Archival Services or RAC Head of Digital Programs for details.
Biographical/Historical note
Wilbur George Downs (1913-1991), an educator and physician, served on the staff of the Rockefeller Foundation (1941-1961) and was associate director of Medical and Natural Sciences from 1961 to 1971. He also served as director of the Virus Research Program in the Division of Biomedical Sciences (1961-1971).
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Wilbur G. Downs and Sonja M. Buckley gave the papers to the Rockefeller Archive Center on November 29, 1984.
Scope and Contents note
The collection includes excerpts from the travel and laboratory diaries (1931-1944) of Rockefeller Foundation personnel, three volumes of correspondence (1940-1970), and a volume of Downs's trip diary with interview notes (1971-1976).
File Plan note
Former Classification: IV 2A 46
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
Materials requiring specialized equipment for access (film, audio, video, slides) may be closed to research dependent on availability of the applicable equipment
Brittle or damaged items, or materials otherwise in need of preservation care, may be closed to researchers at the discretion of the RAC Head of Archival Services/Head of Reference.
Downs, Wilbur G.; Rockefeller Foundation
- Correspondence, 1939-1950, 1967-1974; 1
  Arrangement note
  This series is arranged alphabetically.
  - Buckley, Sonja M., 1969-1974 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Scope and Contents
    Virus research, review of book "Fever," speech by Buckley.
  - Downs, Wilbur G. - Personnel Correspondence (A-L), 1945-1950 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Downs, Wilbur G. - Professional Correspondence - Rockefeller Foundation Staff (A-S), 1939-1950 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Downs, Wilbur G. - Professional Correspondence - Yale Arbovirus Research Unit, 1967-1970; Bound volume. (Box 2, Folder 4)
    Conditions Governing Access
    Restricted material.
- Diaries, 1928-1945, 1971-1976; 2
  - Bauer, Johannes H., March-November 1932 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Bauer, Johannes H., September 1935-December 1936 (Box 3, Folder 5A)
  - Bauer, Johannes H., May-August 1937 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    South American Trip
  - Bauer, Johannes H., January-December 1938 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Bauer, Johannes H., January-December 1939 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Bauer, Johannes H., January-December 1940 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Bauer, Johannes H., January-December 1941 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Bauer, Johannes H., January-December 1942 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Bauer, Johannes H., January 1943-July 1945 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Davis, W. A., December 1942-March 1944 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Downs, Wilbur G. - "Diary and Records of Interviews", 1971-1976; Bound volume. (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Goodner, Kenneth, October 1940-September 1943 (Box 4, Folder 0014A)
  - Hansens, Elton J., October 1943 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Kerr, J. Austin, July-September 1932 (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - L.A.R., April-May 1943 (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Ramsay, George H., June-September 1931 (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Sawyer, Wilbur A., May 1928-August 1935 (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Sawyer, Wilbur A., October 1932-February 1933 (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - Sawyer, Wilbur A., May-August 1934 (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - Vaccine Laboratory, 1940-1943 (Box 4, Folder 22)
- Laboratory Studies, 1940, 1964-1969, 1981, undated; 3
  - Filtration Experiments, 1969 (Box 5, Folder 23)
    Restricted - Confidential material.
  - Isolation Studies, 1969 (Box 5, Folder 24)
  - Lassa Virus - BHK-21, 1969 (Box 5, Folder 25)
  - Lassa Virus - BPL Treated/CF Antigens, 1969 (Box 5, Folder 26)
  - Lassa Virus - Complement-Fixation Test and Growth Curve, 1969 (Box 5, Folder 27)
  - Lassa Virus - Cytopathology, 1969 (Box 5, Folder 28)
  - Lassa Virus - DCA Test, 1969 (Box 5, Folder 29)
  - Lassa Virus - EM Work, 1969 (Box 5, Folder 30)
  - Lassa Virus - Fluorescent Antibody, 1969 (Box 5, Folder 31)
  - Lassa Virus - In A. aeg. Cells, 1969 (Box 5, Folder 32)
  - Lassa Virus - Inactivitation by BPL, 1969 (Box 5, Folder 33)
  - Lassa Virus - Isolation from Mouse Urine, 1969 (Box 5, Folder 34)
  - Lassa Virus - Nucleic Acid Tests, 1969 (Box 5, Folder 35)
  - Lassa Virus - Plaque Test, 1969 (Box 5, Folder 36)
  - Lassa Virus - Stock, 1969 (Box 5, Folder 37)
  - Lassa Virus Protocols - Casals, J. - Blood, 1969 (Box 5, Folder 38)
  - Lassa Virus Protocols - Casals, J. - Cytopathology, 1969 (Box 5, Folder 39)
  - Lassa Virus Protocols - Casals, J. - Lab Reports, 1969 (Box 5, Folder 40)
  - Lassa Virus Protocols - Casals, J. - Neutralization Test, 1969 (Box 5, Folder 41)
  - Lassa Virus Protocols - Casals, J. - Throat Swab, 1969 (Box 5, Folder 42)
  - Lassa Virus Protocols - Casals, J. - Urine Speciman, 1969 (Box 5, Folder 43)
  - Lassa Virus Protocols - Roman, J., 1969 (Box 5, Folder 44)
  - Lassa Virus Protocols - Plaque Reduction Neutralization Tests, 1969 (Box 5, Folder 45)
  - Lassa Virus Protocols - Register of 446 Viruses, 1981 (Box 5, Folder 46)
  - "Materials and Methods" - Manuscript Draft (Box 5, Folder 47)
  - "The Organization and Detailed Procedures of the Vaccine Division of the Yellow Fever Laboratory" - Manuscript Draft, 1940 (Box 5, Folder 48)
    Includes photographs.
  - Studies Relating to the "Nigerian-Lassa Virus", 1964-1969 (Box 5, Folder 49)